this episode is sponsored by indeed
problem indeed prime help software
developers simplify their job search and
land their dream job candidates get
immediate exposure to the best tech
companies with just one simple
application - indeed product companies
on primes exclusive platform message
candidates with salary and equity up
front
the average software developer gets five
employer contacts and an average salary
offer of $125,000 indeed Prime's 100%
free for candidates no strings attached
and when you're hired indeed prime gives
you a two thousand dollar bonus to say
thanks for using primes
but if you use the SE radio link you'll
get a five thousand dollar bonus instead
so sign up at indeed.com / se radio
[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer org
slash software welcome to another show
of software engineering radio today with
me is Patrick qua pet qua welcome to
software engineer radio pet nice to have
you here yeah thank you for having me
it's it's great to talk to you young on
this podcast yeah so who are you whose
pet qualms had quite as a principal
consultant and tech lead for sort works
and he is usually based in London
although he's currently working from
Berlin he has over a decade of
experience in software development he
has a strong focus on people on business
and on technology some of you might know
him for his handbook or retrospective
and the recently published book talking
with tech leads and parrot has also been
involved in giving trainings on
technical leadership both internally to
thwart works as well as externally in
action I was part of one of these
trainings so the topic of this episode
will actually be how to become what is
it about becoming a technical lead so
that's actually perfectly fitting that
is there anything more you would like to
say to yourself I know okay perfect
before we start both me and pet work for
software that's why I attended one of
his trainings um just to keep the lock
clear I would say um and let's just
start with the very first question which
comes into mind when when talking about
becoming a tech lead is what is in the
role of a technical lead what is my
responsibility when I become a technical
lead yeah the question is a really great
one and I think I want to first start
off by saying that the
isn't a single good definition for this
because every organization treats this
role slightly different so what I will
say is having worked with lots of
different clients across different sort
of organizations I can talk about what I
think I see as common characteristics
around what I see a tech leads
responsibility being in some sort of
organizations a tech lead is sometimes
called a lead developer in other
organizations
it is simply called an architect for me
the sort of combination of these two
ideas is that it's not really about an
architect role who's sort of sitting
outside the team but it is actually
about a developer somebody who has
development skills who has the
responsibility of leading the team and
it's quite different I guess from maybe
a senior developer who is maybe leading
us an area within a part of a system but
actually it's really trying to focus on
the sort of effectiveness of a team
overall so I would expect that tech lead
is kind of writing some level of code
and also working at a very technical
level so what I would say a tech leaders
not is sometimes what some people might
be called as a technical manager so
somebody who might be more responsible
for the people a sort of development or
sort of reporting lines but isn't
necessarily concerned about architecture
even though they have that technical
background they aren't necessarily
really focus on where the system is and
I would expect technical managers for
instance to be working with a tech lead
in a lot of other companies I know
masters are very popular roles and I
would actually say that they are
actually sort of a separate roles so
even though a tech lead could be a scrum
master being a scrum master doesn't
necessarily automatically make you a
tech lead mm-hmm so there there's this
aspect of a tech lead is still a
developer and he's focusing on the
effectiveness of the team you say that's
right yeah and you would say a technical
manager is six
krisily focusing on the team and a
architect is exclusively focusing on the
technology and the senior developer is
someone who owns a particular part of
the software when you want to contrast
it yeah that's right and I really want
to emphasize that these are all about
roles and it doesn't necessarily mean
that an organization will have one
person for each of these roles sometimes
person plays multiple of these roles so
sometimes for instance the playing the
tele role may also be the technical
manager looking after sort of the people
landline management and maybe the most
senior developer on the team but there
are other situations where these are for
maybe scale of the team or the way that
the organization has sort of structured
themselves it may be separate roles as
well I typically see I guess a bit more
of a division between sort of the
technical side which is a bit more
around the sort of architecture in the
system direction and more about the sort
of people management and the sort of
project management side which might fall
a bit more into the technical manager
side say that's a bit more of a common
pattern that I would see but I do really
want to emphasize that it is a role and
that means that it's a collection of
responsibilities before we dive deeper
into this can you elaborate a little bit
on why a tech lead is actually needed
yes it's a really great question and
when I've been talking at conferences
about what it's at lead is one of the
first questions I often get is why do we
need this so this is a perfect question
and I can definitely see situations
where if you're working as a small team
and everyone gets along really well and
everyone understands what needs to do
maybe you don't need a tech lead because
everyone understands and is well aligned
in my experience that tends to be a very
idealistic state and there are actually
a lot of teams that sort of maybe in a
more chaotic state and with the mix of
skills so what tends to happen is that
then there's maybe a bit of confusion
about
how things should be implemented or what
the direction of the system and
architecture should be and it's great
when developers who are maybe self
empowered to make choices for themselves
make decisions but when they're working
against each other
you end up with a bit of a mess and for
me one of the key responsibilities of
the tech lead is really keeping the
developers sort of working effectively
in the same direction and you know even
a very stable team who are getting along
one day may end up in a situation where
maybe they disagree about the sort of
way or a framework or a tool that how it
should be implemented or a feature and
you end up sort of with a division and
for me that tight lead role there is to
really Shepherd the team to make sure
that everyone's heading in the same
direction for most effectiveness yeah so
I remember seeing a tweet you share in
your presentation which is like and in
my last project there were 10 guys was
very strong app engine all of that that
were expressed in code is that what
you're hinting at yeah exactly I think
that's a put that tweet in there because
it summarizes it from one different
perspective and I think if you like
conceptually open up a code base that
you don't know maybe you're strangers
and you open up sort of different parts
of the system I think for me a good sign
of effective tech leadership and a team
working together is that in general
everything feels like it's written by
the same sort of developer mindset and
when you have ten different
personalities writing code in different
sort of 10 different ways a it becomes
really difficult maintenance nightmare
and you tend to end up with more silos
which me is worried about overall
effectiveness yeah all right so you have
been a tech lead in multiple locations
so today you're quite experienced but of
course there was a time when you was the
take away you were tech lead for the
very first time can you describe how you
felt and and how it came about yeah
absolutely
um for me I think my first experience
was pretty shocking Angus from I was
just coming back from holiday
I was working on one team and I was I
got a call at the airport saying that'd
be starting as a tech lead for another
team the day that I got back so there
was kind of a bit of a shock effect
about a you know okay I was a developer
on this team now I must do something
different what does that exactly mean
and I think for a lot of people you know
who find themselves in this role they're
probably feeling the same sort of
concern right they maybe they're
confident as themselves as a developer
but then there's a whole bunch of maybe
unexplained responsibilities and what
are the things you should be focusing on
as a tech lead and how is that different
from being in developer so for me I
think a lot of that experience was sort
of trying to work out what that role is
because at that time I didn't really
know where to go for that information
I taught to fortunately other people who
I respected and I had access to to talk
about how they approach it yeah but I
would say that I felt a little bit maybe
unsupported because I didn't have that
sort of safety net where I didn't feel
so safe um but what did the the people
tell you about the tech lead role I
think what was really interesting back
then was I guess some of them talked
about what they felt was really
important and how they approach the role
so I remember one sort of tech lead
talking to me about what they think
about which is the bigger picture and
the architecture so when you're a
developer you know you're probably
thinking a lot more about the clean code
that you're trying to write to make sure
things are testable to make sure that
you're thinking about how well design
that small component is but you
sometimes forget to think about where
that fits in with a bigger picture and
you know I think I feel that in the
agile space we kind of don't talk about
architecture a lot I'm not advocating
for having an architect role and you
know just them focus exclusive on
architecture but I really believe that
actually everyone should be thinking
about architecture and and that's what
part of the architect role helps people
to do on the team it's just sort of come
up at certain points to make sure that
we're sort of still aligned in that same
direction another tip that somebody gave
me was really that focus on
even though you're a tech lead part of
your responsibility is also working with
the rest of the team and so for me this
was actually starting to get some more
awareness of actually as a developer you
know if you see a conflict between two
other people on the team and a common
strategy that you can take is to kind of
just get on with work that you're doing
and you kind of treat that as not your
problem
but actually as a tech lead trying to
resolve perhaps conflict or design
arguments between two developers is
actually an important thing because you
want everyone to sort of agree on the
general direction it doesn't necessarily
matter about which solution is correct
but you're really wanting everyone to at
least have buy-in as to what the general
idea is mmm have you had a conflict in
in your first tech leading gig yeah I
did actually and for me it was like I
think as a developer and having that
sort of technical background I was quite
confident and I guess my more technical
and architecture skills and I guess
dealing with people it made me realize
how actually how different individuals
are and how how strange people can act
when they work with people in different
sort of backgrounds or different skills
and strengths can you highlight that was
an example maybe yeah so I remember a
particular pair on my team and one of
them was very much so we work typically
with pair programming so to developers
sitting at a computer working on the
same sort of story feature and one of
them was kind of a really excited all
kind of person who you know really
wanted to get on with sort of getting on
with work and the other person their
sort of style to development was a lot
more you know I need to actually think
about this problem a little bit I'm
gonna go off and sort of maybe try to
model it a little bit and draw a little
diagram and I'm not talking about you
know they needed weeks or days to go do
this it was really about having some
space and time and I can remember
hearing a couple of frustrations within
sort of the team area about them
you know one person saying I just want
to get on with it and the other person's
like I don't think we're ready for I
don't agree on what we're actually doing
and for me it's just two different
styles but they didn't necessarily
understand that each person had
different styles and hadn't come up with
a way of actually working together yeah
so before that that critical holiday
before that call on the airport how
would you have dealt with this situation
and how did you deal with it as a tech
lead I think if I had dealt with it
before the holiday I would have probably
been in it's not my problem it's the
tech leaders responsibility to sort of
deal with that sort of stuff or maybe a
project manager responsibility to deal
with that so you know the maximum you
would have done is talked was the tech
lead or the project manager yeah I
probably would have flagged it because I
guess it feels a bit strange to maybe
deal with arguments that you're not
involved in hmm
and then I guess post the sort of
holiday and when I was in that role I
guess I felt that it's really important
that every developer can talk to each
other and appreciate each other's
strengths and get along so in this
situation I think I ended up sort of
taking both of the devs into a room to
sort of talk about Frank feedback around
you know what I observed and you know it
wasn't in a way that really tried to
sort of shame them but it was a bit more
of trying to explore where each person
was coming from and where the source of
it was and I think for me it was really
useful for each person to talk about
what was important to them and how they
liked doing things and I think for me
that was a really important thing to be
other then let people air that out in a
bit more of a safer environment mm-hmm
so in the end they agreed on a working
style or yeah so in the end what they
ended up agreeing on was kind of when
they picked up a new bit of work that
you know they would have a certain time
where they would sort of maybe split
their sort of pair and the person who
wanted to sort of get on with it would
maybe pretty type a few things or like
read around some tools and technologies
that were relevant to what they were
going to do and then the other person
would sort of
and sort of draw some sort of models on
some index cards and then they'd get
back together after a couple of hours to
talk through you know how that actually
get implemented mm-hmm yeah that's a
nice story
so we scrabbled on the surface of what
the tas of potentially it's our bye-bye
your first Tech leading test so we have
like you need to see the bigger vision
of of the the project the bigger
architecture and actually we have a nice
episode on architecture sketches by
Simon Brown on there who are also wrote
architecture for developers so it might
be worth listening to it it's shown
number 228 and it's the working with
people aspect you mentioned in in the
conflict example is there or what are
the other responsibilities you see as
the tech lead responsibilities yeah
absolutely
um so on a blog post Simone I have a
model which is like a Venn diagram so if
you look for it you might end up being
answer you connect to it and it's about
the role of a tech lead and what I
described is kind of an overlap of three
circles so one of them is the developer
skills so it's for me really important
that a tech lead can write code and work
with the system that everyone is working
on it doesn't mean that they're only
writing code but they need to be able to
do it and work with the developers at
any point at the same time there's a
circle about general leadership and what
you were kind of talking about was maybe
resolving some sort of conflict but I
think there are a lot of other things
about leadership that effective tech
lead takes on so you know part of some
of the responsibilities will be for
instance trying to convince business
people that you need to spend time as a
team working on technical things because
you need to have that time to make sure
that you're as effective dealing with
maybe technical debt or infrastructure
things that will actually make you a lot
more effective and it's a two-way kind
of street where actually you also need
to be convincing the developers not just
to work on technical things but actually
to also make sure
there is a connection from what they're
working on back into helping the
business because you really want to make
sure you continue to build trust between
sort of the technologists and the
business so there's a kind of bridging
role that our tech lead typically plays
I touched a little bit upon sort of risk
management and I think for me that's a
really big thing that our tech lead
should be really thinking about in most
organizations that role will often have
contact points with other people outside
of the team so maybe it's typically your
operational type people or the support
people who have to run the software that
people build or it's perhaps around sort
of marketing or finance and some of the
implications about the sort of software
or features and it's really about trying
to make sure that overall somebody is
really worrying about risk and some
teams may have a project manager some
people don't and the tech lead also
needs to be thinking about the technical
risks so for instance when people are
putting software into production
is there enough logging infrastructure
in place so that if something goes down
teams know how to support the software
or other people know how to support the
software are we making the right
technical choices such that we're not
necessarily dependent on a particular
vendor roadmap and if they go away then
the software ends up sort of crashing
out or are we spending enough time sort
of keeping our code clean and spending
enough time and refactoring because you
know that will eventually sort of kick
in and sort of kill the effectiveness of
the team so I think this general
leadership type responsibilities and
then the third circle is really around
the architecture so it's really trying
to help people understand more of a
building a system rather than building
software so it's thinking about not just
the features that people are writing on
but also the ecosystem in which that
software is going to live so thinking
about it needs to be deployed on a cloud
or on on a in a docker container stuff
like that absolutely I think it's the
you know and everything is different
some people get to run their own
software or deploy into production other
people don't get to ever see this
we're live as there are different
handoffs to other parts of the
organization but it's really important
that tech leaders trying to help people
understand the consequences of their
feedback and trying to help the
developers get as much feedback about
the software that they write and part of
that is making sure that they understand
what's happening with their software in
production
yeah so they the the block-post you're
you're referencing to is called tech
lead cycles of responsibility I'm gonna
link that in in the show notes
I would like to dive a little bit deeper
into into a few things I saw popping up
there and when I see the leadership and
and also the development thing it's
about object-orientation writing code
evolutionary architecture stuff like
risk management for me it feels like
it's a little bit of managing the team
culture is that something you would
would see as a responsibility yeah
definitely I think team culture is a
really important part and in one of the
talks that I give which is called the
geeks guy to leading teams I talked
about what should a Tetley be focused on
into the team culture and I contrast
that with if you take a team lead you
know they're thinking about how do they
interact with each other and actually as
a tech lead some of the cultural things
that I'm looking for in addition to
those things are thinking about how do
people approach the code that they write
and some some specific examples that I
look for is that you know what sort of
development culture do you want to
cultivate as a tech lead because you can
have that ability to influence that a
concrete example is like if you're doing
continuous integrations builds get
broken you know I've worked on teams
where the the build would stay broken
because it was a bit more of somebody
else's problem type attitude and for me
that was a reflection on you know maybe
a type of team culture that the tech
lead didn't focus on versus other teams
where it's like as soon as it's broken
you know a developer Springs on that and
you know a flag goes up and you know
who's fixing that build yeah what do you
typically do to - yeah support to create
that team culture I think part of a lot
of this stuff is really around bringing
the team to
certain points to to bring alignment so
I think alignment doesn't really happen
if people are sort of working with each
other day to day by itself it can but
more often than not people end up sort
of staying at their computers and maybe
not talking about some of the big issues
so I guess some of the activities that I
think about if you're being an effective
technique is maybe getting the
development team together in a room to
talk about some concerns that make sense
for everyone to get agreement on so for
an example you know you like people
maybe log things in different formats
and maybe the discussion is around okay
what's our general approach to logging
and how do we make sure that we log the
right level in information other ways of
getting alignment for instance getting a
developer to maybe share a certain part
of the system maybe it's about
interacting with external API s or other
external dependencies and to see if
there's a general consistent approach in
that you know you might actually find
even in a team of eight people you end
up with three different strategies for
dealing with external systems and people
can learn from that yeah so what I hear
you saying is a little bit what I'm
familiar as heck Huddle's where the team
gets together and talks about
technologies is that a little bit but
what you're hinting yet yeah definitely
and that is I guess one name and maybe
one way of achieving that you know some
of the teams do a whole group code
reviews and there's a company in the UK
andrew lee who's kind of known for i
guess trying to push extreme programming
even more to the point where you know
they've adopted quite regularly mob
programming or the entire team is sort
of programming at the same time let's
move on from teams culture to something
else i I heard you talking about which
is growing the developer growing people
I guess that's something of a business
of a fatigue lead how do you approach
that typically yeah well I would
actually say why it's important first is
a very common anti pattern that I see
with particularly new tech needs is that
a lot of companies tend to promote maybe
the best developer into this role and I
don't actually think you need to be the
best developer on the team to play this
role I think you need to be a good
developer that everyone respects but I
don't think you necessarily need to be a
best developer and I think one of the
consequences of when the best developer
is promoted into the team is that
they'll want to keep writing all the
code the best that they can and what
that ends up doing is creating a sort of
bad systemic cycle where you know they
want to take maybe all the interesting
problems they want to tackle all the
hard solutions and you know kind of
leave the easy stuff for the rest of the
developers now if you flip it around the
other side and you think you're a
developer on that team you know it's not
very inspiring or exciting to be working
on things that aren't so interesting at
the same time the tech lead in this sort
of bad anti-pattern is maybe torn in
lots of other meetings and other things
because they have other responsibilities
to deal with and so it's really hard for
them to actually do a really good job as
they whereas just focusing as a
developer so that's why I think it's
important to build the other developers
how you go how you go to develop new
developers is I guess really trying to
help people connect to maybe new
opportunities that they've not done and
give them a safety blanket around that
so you know encouraging people to work
on areas or technologies that they've
not dealt with but maybe they have you
know either yourself or other people to
bounce ideas off and just sort of
strategize about approaches can you
share an example how you've done that
maybe with someone yeah absolutely
so on one of the teams that I've worked
with we introduced the concept of sort
of feature leads and the idea was for me
to sort of make sure that as a tech lead
I had a still good overview of how we
were going to approach a certain area
and then each sort of developer got to
maybe own kind of a feature and how we
would actually end up implementing that
to the area as an example maybe like how
we approached authentication in this
particular example and then what that
ended up doing is that I would actually
pair people up just so that they have
that sort of support and they'd sort of
go off explore what we kind of needed in
terms of this particular authentication
they talk about what tools
libraries we might end up using how
would approach er and what are the
potential ways that would end up writing
or designing our code to deal with that
at which point then I got to sort of
maybe help review some of that stuff to
make sure there was no gaps and to make
sure that it seems to make sense in
alignment with other things and then
when we were happy with that solution we
then doubled that up with maybe what you
would have called a tech huddle then
sort of got the whole team involved to
make sure they understood what the
general approach would be and I guess
what was really interesting is that some
feature leads were maybe a lot more
successful in terms of being able to
come up with a solution by themselves
whereas other people needed a little bit
more time in terms of saying you know I
don't really know where to go about even
starting about how to break this down
and then would work together on maybe
different approaches or you know
different options that they could
explore and so you know this is helping
people grow and people will need
different ways of getting there yeah so
this feature lead strategy was basically
giving people explicit responsibilities
in the team and then supporting the ones
who who struggled was with that
responsibility to do it completely on
their own yeah absolutely yeah how do
you support me so if I'm taking over the
future lead for authentication and I'm I
don't know how to start what would you
say to me yeah so I guess partly I'd
sort of explain what I expected future
lead which is around making sure that we
meet all the requirements from the
business side and assess all the
potential risks of what type of
authentication use cases we actually
need so part of it would be saying okay
you probably need to talk to these sorts
of people to get an understanding about
how they want to interact with the
system and then you know sort of they go
off in sort of it look at that sort of
area and then talk about okay what what
sort of approach do you think we take
from a technical perspective and if
there wasn't any sort of you know I
think part of the habits of a good tech
leaders not giving all the answer
straightaway but letting people find the
answers for themselves and so I do a lot
of sort of questioning to work out where
people are comfortable and what
knowledge they already have and if they
don't know at all where to start
like the example you gave then I might
be a little bit more
directive and say okay well have you
considered say looking at a war and
these libraries in this sort of area and
you know all these you know do we need
two factor authentication and then you
know people go off and sort of evaluate
that sort of fit based on the technology
stack that we have it might even involve
sort of saying okay you know go off and
run a spike which is a time boxed
technical investigation where somebody
comes up with a small prototype and then
we come back and we learn a little bit
about that yeah typically when when I'm
in in such a situation I typically tell
the people oh that's the terms I would
start googling for is that something you
would also do yeah that's definitely an
option yeah yeah all right so we
mentioned future leech with which
essentially is you look at the
responsibility as a tech lead and find a
certain area where you say I do like
delegate that to to someone to grow him
or her it's they're also an aspect of
choosing the right person for that job I
think I prefer a bit more of a pool
model in terms of sort of like I guess
my goal is a set leaders I want everyone
to buy into the work that they're doing
because I want people who care about
that so for a lot of the sort of points
I try to avoid explicitly choosing
people and I try to get people who want
to work in that area and part of the
role I guess which is a communication
skill is trying to get people excited
about what is interesting around
different areas because I think
sometimes you can get really talking
about what's not right in different
systems or you know that we have to get
on with this work but at the same time
some of this stuff needs to get done and
there are other opportunities to do it
so I prefer to sort of say okay you know
we need to look at how campaign
management and we need to come up with a
way of how we actually integrate that
technical solution with how we're going
to run campaigns across this particular
product we need somebody to come up with
this technical solution and the general
approach of how we deal with this you
know and here are maybe the exciting
opportunities and the people you get to
work with that you don't necessarily
normally get to and then I look for
volunteers and you know sometimes you
don't have volunteers at which point you
might need to then choose people
but then part of that comes down to you
as a leader building up that trust with
the developers on your team mmm is have
you ever been in the situation where you
felt that someone volunteer to off yes
definitely
and I would often sort of say that
explicitly so I guess part of me is that
Hedley training to support people being
successful is also watching how much
stuff that they take on and trying to
manage that as well so I think on one of
the teams that I worked on I think we
had a kind of guideline rule that nobody
should be working on more than two
feature areas at one time hmm just
because there's too much work yeah I
remember from from our trainings that
you also are very deliberate in knowing
where people want to develop can you
elaborate a little bit on that yeah
absolutely and I think this is something
about getting to know your people and a
tool that you can use is really just
spending one-on-ones with people and you
know asking people about what are they
interested in and where do they want to
develop in and when you sort of ask
people that a a lot of people don't
often really have an answer because they
don't really think about it some people
will have very clear goals and so some
of it is really trying to explore what
are people interested in whatever may be
their concrete goals and you know where
do they see themselves going and I'm
looking at as a tech lead for a lot of
alignment between the sort of work
that's going on that is available in the
environment in which we are as well as
the things and opportunities that people
would like that maybe they're not yet
aware of so as an example you know I
have had some developers that really
wanted to get into sort of this DevOps
mindset of really working with
infrastructure working with sort of
automations a popular chef or trying to
actually work on that sort of stuff
whereas other developers really don't
want to deal with that you know they
want to focus on maybe more of the front
end kind of UI type stuff or you know
you have developers who don't really
want to look at UI type stuff but really
just want to get better at maybe the
hardcore back-end services and api's and
unless you ask people you don't really
find
about these things and and this is where
it's really useful to sort of spend time
with sort of each developer and you know
maybe even do it as a group as well
mm-hmm yeah all right again switching
topic a little bit you mentioned it in
the beginning as a tech lead you need to
go to yourself yes why is that so yeah
um so I think it's a really key thing
and and I think for me it's really about
being able to code with the system I
have a article that I sort of refer to
which was I think from computer world or
info world and in it this sort of author
talks about how you know developers tend
to respect to other developers because
they can see the code that they write
and I have an example very early on from
my career where I was working in a
company where there were sort of
technical managers and one of the sort
of technical managers wanted me to sort
of finish this tool which would kind of
connect back then sort of CVS into their
internal source control system okay and
it was with Perl bindings and all this
sort of stuff and it was late Friday and
and this manager came up and said okay
okay it's really important that we get
this done before the end of the day and
you know we're talking about 3:00 p.m.
on a Friday afternoon and I'm pretty
confident we're not gonna get it done
and I was like okay well let's work on
this together and we sit there and then
you know he sort of handed over the
keyboard to the technical manager and
there was just this kind of like look of
what do I do next like and it was just
clear to me that you know he couldn't
write any Perl and it wasn't clear to me
what he wanted to do achieve by sitting
down and pairing with me on this sort of
the stuff and I recognize this as a
developer early in my career is that
this okay I'm putting this person into
the non-technical bucket over here and
at that point you know you end up having
a very different perspective and so as a
tech lead if you if your developers
don't respect the fact that you can
write the system when you're helping
them try to make choices as a group
about the different direction
you know you'll end up probably making
the wrong decisions and also the or
developers probably won't have buy-in
and so for me it's really important that
a tech lead and
stands what's going in the code and so
you know you'll probably get more used
to reading code than writing code but I
still think it's really important that a
Tetley can contribute to the system so
you know they know where to go for a
particular area and they know how to
sort of add extra features in where
tests would go and be able to do that
because it's really important for
maintaining that rapport and also just
the awareness of the general technical
architecture and risk yeah so I need a
need to code because I need to be
respected by the developers to be a
successful tech lead the second aspect
is was you just mentioned in the end
like you also need to know what is going
on in the code to be a tech lead yeah
absolutely and I I see this quite a lot
as well in you know tech leads
particularly maybe the too much of a
offhand hit lead where they you know
trust the team they do that and then
they come to the team and look at the
codebase six months later and then say
why have we got classes that are three
hundred lines long and what where are
the sort of tests and where are these
expectations of what they thought was
good code but hasn't really been
happening so much because the the team
have may be making that decision and for
me this is about that technical risk
management which is you know it's great
that you trust developers and you want
to give people that sort of
understanding and freedom at the same
time you also need a feedback loop to
validate that you know what you think is
happening is actually happening and I
think for me that's a really key thing
where as I said you need to be able to
understand what this is the current
state of the system is to see if the
balance is maybe going too far of yeah
we're pushing out features too fast and
we actually need to spend some time and
maybe redesigning and you know maybe we
need to look at a different
architectural approach for one part of
the system rather than just keep adding
to what we currently have so when you
code as a tech lead is it pairing or is
it single-handed coding or is it other
types of coding it's a great question
and I would highly recommend staying
away from the being the lone ranger
working on it's really critical time
critical tasks because you end up being
a blocker so
naturally I think one of the
difficulties which I think we'll talk a
bit about later is about time management
and it means that you won't really be
able to continue working on something so
you should really try to avoid working
on kind of the critical path item and I
find pairing is a really great way of
working so one of the ways that I like
to work with people is I guess typically
when we sit down with a feature or user
story we're kind of talking about our
general approach what we need to do and
we're a little bit more explicit about
some of the things that would like to
approach so that if I end up sort of
being interrupted which I never Libby
will or have to go to a meeting then you
know you can do that things kind of
continuing and when you come back
hopefully things haven't veered off to
course or at least you can have a
conversation with who you're working
with and it has a benefit of a couple of
things where you know the person that
you're working with gets to get some
extra input from a different perspective
but also that you know you you get that
to the touch point with sort of features
and and you know what's going on in the
codebase so you're learning a little bit
the implementation pass when you start a
pairing so that the other person can
continue on its own and you have to to
go to a meeting yeah so I want to
highlight another pad anti-pattern
because I think it's really critical
here and it actually happened on the
project where I was a developer just
before I became the tech lead for the
first time and my tech lead at that time
had an interesting style of dealing with
things they didn't like which meant that
we would sort of go home in the evening
as developers and they would sort of
magically refer to everything away in
there in the middle of the night check
it in and when we came in the morning
we'd be looking at the code and saying
well why is it all been rewritten and
there was no discussion about why it was
done or if it was even better because
for us it was really puzzling and very
difficult to maintain and it created
this sort of sense of disempowerment so
I really want to highlight that as a
really big key tech lead anti-pattern
over like rewriting everyone's code
because you disagree with it
mm-hmm yeah this leads very nicely into
into another area because
you when you when you are a developer
usually you have peers around you and
suddenly in the situation you described
there is the developers and the tech
lead and I've heard you talking about
tech lead being a lonely role so how
much is tech lead part of the team and
how much is it really different from the
the developer team yeah um I I think so
for me I think the tech lead is part of
the team I think some of the
responsibilities and a different
perspective means that you kind of felt
you feel torn between two worlds so
there's one part where you are working
with the team writing code but then at
the same time you are often drawn into
other things where you know maybe the
business sort of screaming for new
features and sort of pressure of
delivering new things or you know maybe
a developer has come to you with a
sensitive topic about what's concerning
them and it's really difficult to share
that with everyone else because of you
know that personal nature and I think
this is where you feel both part of the
team but also at the same time outside
and as a developer who's maybe moved
into this role that can be really hard
so there are a lot of other roles and
development teams which are typically
maybe a bit more unique so maybe you
have only just one test or maybe you
only have one sort of project manager
but as a developer away you're normally
surrounded by lots of other developers
and you feel put into this role where
you're both still part of the team but a
little bit out you can feel very lonely
hmm and apart from feeling lonely what
does this mean for you when you're
becoming at that need yeah um I guess
some of the things I learned the hard
way is that you can deal with the
problems yourself and you can kind of
keep thinking you know you have to you
know you've been put in this position
for reason so you're competent of being
able to do this but it's really
important that you actually build your
own sort of support network and what
that means is for some topics it's often
better to talk with other people who
aren't associated with your current
environment and this is where I kind of
talk about a lot in the courses that I
lead which was around building your own
support network in some organizations
you may be lucky that you're working
with other tech leads from other teams
or you have lots of tech leads and the
same floor
and in those situations you have the
real benefit of maybe beyond to
coordinate something what we used to do
called tech lead lunches you know or a
tech lead sort of session where you get
them all together and you sort of get to
talk about a few more of the things
that's difficult to talk about with your
team you know it might be about managing
your time and your calendar and how you
sort of cope we're getting back into
code maybe it's about you know what's
the best way of getting over some
conflict in the teams or you know what
tools and technologies are other teams
using that makes sense that maybe we
aren't even aware of because we don't
have people who know about them but
things that are just really difficult to
get that sort of feedback from within
the team and you need that sort of
support yeah I actually was once in a
meeting where where someone asks ok who
have you as a manager who's developer
and who is a here's an architect and he
said manager is the one where you are
most of the time in your email so
developers most of the time in the IDE
and a architect is most of the time in
PowerPoint and I actually said oh and
that tech lead is the most of the time
in his calendar so is that something you
discuss in those lunches and you may
share some some discussions you had in
this lunches yeah the way that I
facilitated it is because obviously we
we thought works for a consultancy so we
work with different clients but I was
lucky enough to be close to other teams
who are working with close clients in
this or the neighborhood so we got
together at lunchtime because that was
the easiest way for us to meet somewhere
neutral and then we try to focus on a
topic of the day so you know like we all
brought like we had a list sort of like
a Trello board or a list of topics we
wanted to talk about so I think one of
the topics of the time was like time
management you know how do you get
yourselves away from meetings there was
another topic which was maybe about
dealing with so developer issues so you
know maybe there's a developer that's
maybe not gelling with the rest of the
team what are the strategies that other
people would use to maybe help get some
more online mentor and that sort of
stuff sometimes it was like really
technical kind of topics right which is
like let's you know review our
architecture and
see if it makes sense or would you have
approached our problem a different way
and yeah we'd sort of pick a topic that
we we try not to focus on things that
were very very developer centric so
because otherwise you could talk with
that with your team like you know what's
the right design pattern for this
particular feature or whatever and we
really try to focus on issues that we
felt were most valuable to share with
peers at the same level yeah all right
that seems to be a nice energy to build
a support network so let's let's look at
the processes of how to become a tech
lead so there was this call on on the
airport once you came back from from
holidays and you buy one call you were
transformed from a developer into a tech
lead kind of have you been working
towards it or did it happen to you uh I
think it was yes rust upon me is
probably the best way of describing it
and I think for me I didn't really know
where to go for support other than
talking to people and I'm thankful that
I had people to talk to but it would
have also been a lot better had I been
able to sort of maybe been aware about
what the responsibilities were and
understand how to do that
I think post that experience I ended up
looking for books around that area and
probably one of the oldest books that I
found was becoming a technical leader by
Gerald Weinberg which i think was a
really great book and gives you lots of
toolkits but I think it really helps all
sorts of people in any sort of technical
environment not necessarily just tech
leads and so for me I think there was a
bit of a gap in terms of helping people
understand what does it mean to be
really sort of successful tech lead I
guess which is one of the reasons I
ended up sort of studying the book which
is a collection interviews called
talking with tech leads yeah we'll
quickly talk about the book later I
wonder when you suddenly start being
another role what are the things you you
notice you what what are the things
suddenly different you when when you
become a tech need yes is it I mean it's
not like you're different person from
one to the other day
you know I think part of the struggle is
first when somebody sort of gives you
these roles is there's a certain
uncertainty and you know there's
potentially a lot of stress going am I
actually doing what I should be doing
and you know it's very difficult to
sometimes get a list of responsibilities
or areas in which you should focus on
say I think for me it was really not
really aware about the things I didn't
know and I was conscious that there were
probably things that I should be looking
at but maybe didn't know about and I was
really trying to find and talk to people
about you know what are those things
that I'm not doing but maybe I should be
doing at the same time I guess I was
really trying to throw myself into
understanding you know okay I feel
comfortable in my sort of developer
level skills
there's definitely leadership skills in
terms of the lead of the role so what
does that mean and where can I go to
find and develop those things so you
know understanding how you communicate
effectively particularly with say
non-technical stakeholders versus
technical ones you know how do you
resolve conflict how do you start
influencing people rather than sort of
you know being able to do that's
recurred and then also what does the
sort of technical leadership
architecture stuff mean so trying to
really focus at the one on building up
skills around that area yeah it's there
something the developers on your team
did that helped you in this
transformation process or is there
something developers could do in general
when they see they have a newbie tech
lead to support him
yeah I mean if I think back to a couple
of my teams I think the things that
helped me as a Tetley is making sure
that I get feedback from various sources
and one of my favorite tools for doing
this is maybe as part of the one-on-ones
or maybe as part of a different session
which is doing sort of 360 degree
feedback cycles so I think sometimes we
can go away and I've seen this with
other tech needs where you know they
think they're doing a great job but
actually the developers have a different
perspective and I think it's really
important that as the tech lead you
ground yourself in getting that feedback
about what the perspective is from your
developers it's hard to do if you
haven't built up that trust
I think it's really important and it
deepens that trust once you have that
respect with your team if you can
actually talk about you know what do you
see me doing as a tech lead and your
expectations and am i fulfilling them or
where do you think I may be weaker or I
could improve on and where are the
things that you think I am actually
doing a pretty good job and so you can
get some more perspective around that
and to sort of validate that across the
team yeah so getting feedback is an
important tool what kind of feedback did
you get if you're if you would like to
share some of it yeah um so I had some
feedback from my team so this is a kiss
a personal thing about when I contacts
which a lot
I am very task-oriented and so I end up
getting very I guess it's maybe a bit
more directive and I guess this was some
of the feedback that I got which is
particularly when I'm stressed you know
I may be doing give enough time for
people to talk about this sort of story
or the pain points and I'm really
focused on what are we doing about it
and I think for me that was really
useful sort of check-in point because a
when you're under stress you don't
realize how much that's affecting your
behavior and we all have different
coping mechanisms for that but also then
that also helps me understand what's not
working with the team and we end up
agreeing on a mechanism for me to sort
of both deal with the stress in terms of
the context switching by having sort of
more specific times where maybe I could
be more interrupted and times where I
needed just to really focus on maybe
thinking about a couple of bigger issues
and then also it made me a lot more
aware of how is interacting with people
when I was under stress so it meant that
I try to give people more time and
empathize with a sort of current
situation rather than trying to drive
for a particular solution hmm all right
let's start going a little bit into
summary and there is one question I
think is nagging around when you're
doing tech lead for the first time or
even today which is how do I know that
I'm good when I'm tech leading
I think it's a great question I've never
really thought about that what I would
say is everyone has a different
technical leadership style say I think
what good looks like you have to kind of
I guess appreciate or recognize how you
approach stuff I think a good sign that
a tech lead is working is that you kind
of don't really need the tech lead from
a day to day perspective so I think if a
tech lead is kind of constantly involved
in meetings and constantly giving the
answers to everything I would say that
they're probably not being so effective
as a tech lead so if we go back maybe
connecting to maybe one of the first
questions that you asked which is why do
we even need a set lead is that I guess
if you're a being an effective Tetley
the tech lead role should be a bit more
of a you can go back to being a
developer role still focusing on that
sort of bigger picture and watching for
whether there's misalignments but if
you're doing your job effectively then
the team should be aligned and there
shouldn't be so many sort of arguments
and or they can resolve it themselves
and there is that general consensus
mm-hmm okay so you you've wrote a book
it's called talking with tech leads from
novices to practice and you've been
interviewing a lot of tech leads always
asking the same few set of questions and
there is you have multiple perspectives
of how a tech lead can be in this book
and what I actually like about it is it
shows very concrete that every tech leaf
has his own style hmm
what did you learn doing those
interviews yeah I mean it's it's it's
well actually I think the first part is
what you you already answered which is
actually there's different approaches to
to taking this on and each one is okay
and I think that's okay
is that I think when you move into that
role you'll question yourself about am i
doing the right things and you will have
your own style and just because the tech
lead and the different team approaches
it differently doesn't mean you're doing
it wrong but I think for me it was
really
really understanding that there are
different tools and approaches that
people use and there are different
focuses so I think for me one of the
biggest takeaways was when I am in these
roles being a tech lead I don't make
enough time for myself and I think that
was an interesting observation from I
think it was John pillar in the book
where you know it was really he was
focused very much from sort of the
meditation and being in the moment and
trying to make sure that he has that
time to focus on what he's doing right
and to prioritize your time and I think
for me that was one of my biggest
takeaways out of that book which was
making sure that you make enough time
for yourself you how many techniques
have you been talking this at the moment
yeah
I ended up talking to about I think 37
different tech leads and there was a few
more but I think I was trying to get for
some some depth I also tried to really
focus on trying to find female tech
leads it was really interesting because
as an industry we have a problem with
sort of trying to get enough sort of
female developers but killings for the
female tech leads into the book for me
was a personal goal and that was really
interesting trying to reach out to my
network of people about who I could talk
to you around that yeah so what did the
the different tech leads talk about what
were the main topics you see yeah so the
book is split into two areas one which
is focus and novices and the people
who've maybe been doing it for a while
which have been labeled as practitioners
and you know I guess it was really
interesting because with the novices
there was a lot of commonality around
that shock which was the you know I've
been a developer I'm now an estate lead
role what does it mean and actually for
me it was great to hear that everyone
had the same sort of struggles because I
hope that that helps people recognize
that if you move into that role for the
first time it's the normal thing of
being in that role and that's okay in
the sort of second part of the book
there was some emergent themes that kind
of came out and there was definitely one
which was about sort of managing
yourself
which was a whole sort of theme and this
was really trying to focus on
prioritizing your time making sure that
you understood you know where you're
spending on time to be most effective
and actually it's okay to sort of spend
time sort of planning where you spend
your time and I think that's really
important there was a whole section
around people and I think for developers
this will probably one of the more
difficult parts to develop so I think
developers will naturally move towards
maybe more technical type sort of
architectural thinking which is the tech
of a tech lead another section but I
think understanding people and dealing
with difficult people circumstance is
like something you don't really practice
as a developer so you don't have that
experience to build on and you'll need
that when you actually move into that
role the final sort of category was
really around bridging sort of tech with
the business so we haven't really talked
about it much in the sort of context
because I think we felt a little bit
more inwards and on this architecture
and technical side but there's a really
key thing where the tech lead role in a
lot of organizations is about this sort
of bridging with the business so trying
to make sure that there's a close
connection to what the that's sort of
technical team and delivering to
business value and helping the business
understand what the technical terms mean
what the architecture means and what
decisions what the implications of
decisions are and how they affect
potential business opportunities hmm
that was my last question so that now is
your opportunity to ask to any
questioner should have actually asked is
there something you want to say in the
end some final lasts pearls of wisdom
yeah I guess my advice to people who
wanted to fill up themselves this
Headley bit is that I hope that a lot of
the sort of mapping out about what a
Tetley should do is a little bit clearer
through sort of some of the work that
I've been trying to focus on and I hope
that it really helps people start to
understand that it is a map of
differences of skills in areas and then
you can find ways of developing and
finding ways of sort of practicing some
of those skills to make it explicit I
definitely sort of say make sure that
you know you build up your own support
network
and that's a really key thing and that
actually being it at league should infer
thing because some people think that
sometimes you move post technical but
actually it is about having a really
positive impact because you know as a
developer you get really frustrated
sometimes about your environment but
actually is a tech lead you get to help
shape that and I think that's a really
exciting opportunity mm-hmm all right
thank you very much how can people find
out more about this topic so there's
obviously the book they can buy and read
yep you can so I tend to blog a lot or
maybe not a lot but quite frequently on
these sorts of topics about technical
leadership on my website which is
www.hyken.com
you know I think I learned a lot by
talking to people about you know the
problems are they're having and I love
to share my experiences so do reach out
my Twitter handles Pat quoi yeah and of
course there's the the book website
which you can find on lean pub all right
yeah so the next thing would be not to
reach out to you and all of that will
obviously be in our show notes so we
will link the blog post mentions and and
also pets website as well as Twitter
profile being a vet
thank you very much Pat for this
interview I think it was very very
interesting thank you for having me it's
you've had some really great questions
and I've really enjoyed the discussion
thank you very good so we as su radio of
course want to hear what you think of
this show and all the other shows so
reach out to us use the comments on the
website to comment on this episode we
have a team email which is team at se -
radio net we have a Twitter handle which
is at se radio you can find us on
LinkedIn Google+ Facebook just let us
know what you you think of us that would
really really help us so was that I
think thank you for today this is your
Hannah
for software engineering radio thanks
for listening bye thanks for listening
the SC radio an educational program
brought to you by I Triple E software
magazine for more information about the
podcast including other episodes visit
our website @ SC - radio name to provide
feedback you can write comments on each
episode on the website or write a review
on itunes mention a message us on
twitter at SC radio or search for the
software engineering radio group on
LinkedIn Google+ or Facebook you can
also email us at team @ SC - radio net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons 2.5
license thanks again for your support
[Music]
[Applause]
you
[Music]